<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Dialog team="1">
	<Participants>
		<Person nickname="Leibniz"/>
		<Person nickname="Clarke"/>
	</Participants>
 Leibniz-Clarke papers G. W. Leibniz and Samuel 
Clarke Clarke 1: (26.xi.1715) 
<Body>
<Turn nickname="Leibniz" nr="1">Leibniz's first paper (November 1715)
		<Utterance genid="1" ref="-1"> 1  Natural religion seems to be 
greatly on the decline -in England-, where many people hold that human souls are made of matter, and 
others contend that God himself is a corporeal being, -i.e. a body-. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="2" ref="-1">2 Locke and his  followers aren't sure 
whether the soul is material and naturally perishable. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="3" ref="-1">3 Newton says that 
space is an organ-like a sense-organ- by which God senses things. But if God  needs an organ to sense things by, it follows that they don't depend entirely on him and weren't produced by him.
		<!-- Clarke  translates Leibniz as speaking of how God &apos;perceives&apos; things; but the verb Leibniz uses is  sentir, a cognate of sens (&apos;sense&apos;), so that &apos;sense&apos; seems right. In his 87 on page 43, Leibniz says that this verb  shouldn&apos;t be used for what God does unless it is purged of its implication of passivity; and it&apos;s just a fact  about word-usage at that time that the tie between -sensing and -being acted on was much stronger and more obvious that  any tie between -perceiving and -being acted on. -->
		</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="4" ref="-1">4 Newton and his followers also have a very odd opinion regarding God's 
workmanship. According to them, God's watch -the universe- would stop working if he didn't  re-wind it from 
time to time! He didn't have enough foresight to give it perpetual motion. This  machine that he has made is 
so imperfect that from time to time he has to clean it by a miraculous  intervention, and even has 
to mend it, as a clockmaker mends his work. The oftener a clockmaker has to adjust his machine and set it  right, the clumsier he must be 
as a clockmaker! In my view, the world always contains the same -amount of- force and  energy, which changes only by 
passing from one material thing to another in accordance with the laws of nature and the  beautiful order -that 
			God has- pre-established. And I hold that when God works miracles, he does it  not to meet the needs 
of nature
			but to meet the needs of grace. Anyone who thinks differently must have  a very mean notion of 
the wisdom and power of God.</Utterance>
	</Turn>
	<Turn nickname="Clarke" nr="1">Clarke's first reply (26 November 1715)	
	<Utterance genid="5" ref="1">1 
Some  people in England (and in other countries!) reject natural religion or get it all wrong; that is very true, and much to be lamented. 
			But. . . this is largely due to the false philosophy of the materialists-a philosophy that clashes more directly than any 
other  with the mathematical principles of philosophy. It's also very true that some people say that the soul
			s of men are bodies, and others say this even about God himself; but those who do so are the  
great enemies of the mathematical principles of philosophy-principles that prove that matter (or  
body) is the smallest and most inconsiderable part of the universe.</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="6" ref="2"> 2 Locke did write some things implying that he wasn't sure  
whether the -human- soul was immaterial or not; but the only people who have followed him in this are  
some materialists, who are enemies to the mathematical principles of philosophy, and who accept little or nothing from  
Locke except his errors.</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="7" ref="3"> 3 Newton doesn't say that space is the organ God uses to perceive  
things by, or that God needs any medium by which to perceive things. Quite the contrary! His view is that because 
			God is omnipresent--present everywhere--he perceives all things just by being -immediately present to them, i.e. by  
being exactly where they are, wherever in space that might be; and for this he doesn't need the help of an organ  (or 
anything else) to -mediate between himself and the things he perceives. Trying to make this easier to grasp, Newton illustrates it by  a 
comparison: The mind of man is immediately present to the pictures or images of things that are formed in the brain by means of the  
sense-organs, and it -immediately- sees those pictures. and similarly: God is immediately present to all things in the  
universe, and immediately sees those things. (Whereas God immediately perceives the things, the human mind perceives  
the pictures as if they were the things.) In the human case, Newton regards the brain and sense-organs as the means by which -those  
pictures are formed, not as the means by which -the mind perceives those pictures once they have been formed. And in God
's case, Newton doesn't regard things as if they were pictures that had been formed by certain means or organs; he regards them  as real 
things that God himself -has formed and -sees in all the places where they are, without the help of any  intermediary. 
This comparison is all that he means when he supposes infinite space to be (as it were) the sensorium of -God
			-, the omnipresent being. <!-- In one of its two main meanings, &apos; sensorium &apos; stood for the part of the  brain where 
sensory images (or their material counterparts or underlays) occur. There was no standard view about what part of the brain  this was; but 
it was assumed that there must be one - sensory images had to have their brain counterparts somewhere, and  &apos;sensorium&apos; was the 
name of the appropriate &apos;somewhere&apos;. -->
		</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="8" ref="4"> 4 Among humans, the maker of a machine is rightly  regarded as skillful in 
proportion to how long a machine that he has made will work properly without any further tinkering by him. Why? It 's because he exercises 
his skill only in constructing, adjusting, or putting together certain moving parts-such as weights and  springs-whose source of motion is 
a set of forces that are entirely independent of him; he arranges them in various  ways, but he didn't 
make them. But with regard to God, the case is quite  different: as well as assembling things into 
structures, he is himself the author and continual preserver of their basic forces or powers of motion. So the fact 
that nothing happens without his continual regulation and oversight is a -true glory of his  workmanship and not -something that detracts 
from it. The idea that the world is a great machine that goes on without intervention by God, like a clock ticking 
along without help from a clockmaker-that's the idea of materialism and fate. Under  cover of declaring God to be a 
supra-mundane intelligence <!-- = &apos;a thinking being who is above the world&apos; -->, it aims to exclude providence and God
			's government from the world. And the reasoning that will lead The passage  referred to is as follows: 'The sensory <!-- = 
&apos;sensorium&apos; --> of animals is the place -in the brain- to which the sensing  mind is present, and into which the sensible 
species of things <!-- roughly = &apos;whatever it is that perceived things transmit to the  sense-organs&apos; --> are carried through 
the nerves and brain, so that they can be perceived there because of their immediate presence  to that mind.' a philosopher to maintain 
that From the beginning of creation, everything has happened without any regulation or  intervention by God, will 
enable a sceptic to argue back further, maintaining that From all eternity things have gone  on as they now do, without any real creation 
or any creator, depending on nothing but an all-wise and eternal 'Nature'. Suppose a king had a kingdom 
in which everything continually went on without his regulation or  interference-without his attending to and ordering what is done in his 
realm-it would be a 'kingdom' only in name, not in  reality, and this 'king' wouldn't deserve that title. -Well, there's no smoke without 
a fire-! If someone claims that  in an earthly government things can go on perfectly well without the king's ordering or dealing with 
anything, we can reasonably  suspect him of wanting to get rid of the king altogether. Similarly, anyone who maintains that the world can 
continue to run its course  without the continual direction of God the supreme governor has a doctrine that does have 
the effect of excluding God from the world.</Utterance>
	</Turn>
	<Turn nickname="Leibniz" nr="2">Leibniz's second paper <Utterance genid="9" ref="5">To Clarke's 1 
			<page n="1"/> 1 I agree. . . that  the principles of the materialists contribute greatly to the spread of impiety. 
			But I see no reason to add  that the mathematical principles of philosophy are -opposite to those of the 
materialists. Really they are -the same,  with just this difference: The materialists who follow Democritus, Epicurus and Hobbes confine 
themselves altogether to mathematical principles <!-- i.e. to physics, with no admixture of anything else --> , and 
hold that nothing exists but bodies; whereas the Christian mathematicians
			<!-- i.e. Newton and his 
followers --> allow that there are also  immaterial substances. What ought to be set up against materialism, therefore, are not -
mathematical principles (taking  this phrase in its usual sense) but rather -metaphysical principles. 
Pythagoras, Plato, and Aristotle had some knowledge  of metaphysical principles, but I claim to have established them in 
my book Theodicy; it is written in an informal manner  for the general reader, but my proof is perfectly rigorous. The 
great foundation of mathematics is the  principle of contradiction or identity, i.e. that a proposition can't be true 
and false at the same time, so that  A is A and can't be not-A. This principle is all we need to demonstrate every part 
of arithmetic and geometry, i.e. to demonstrate  all mathematical principles. But, as I pointed out in 
Theodicy, the move from mathematics to natural philosophy <!-- here = &apos;physics&apos; --> requires a further 
principle, namely the principle of the need for a  sufficient reason, which says that for anything that is the case there's a reason why 
it should be so rather than otherwise. That is  why Archimedes, wanting to move on from mathematics to natural 
philosophy in his book on equilibrium, had to use a  special case of the great principle of sufficient reason. Suppose you have a 
perfectly symmetrical balance and that you put equal weights  in its two pans. Nothing will move; and Archimedes saw why-it's because no 
reason can be given why one side should go down rather  than the other. Using just that one principle-that there has to be a sufficient 
reason why things should be as they are and not  otherwise-we can demonstrate the existence of God and all the rest of 
metaphysics and natural theology. We can even  demonstrate, in a way, principles of natural philosophy that don't depend on 
mathematics-I mean the dynamic  principles, i.e. the principles of force. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="10" ref="5">2 Clarke goes on to say that 
according to Newton's physics matter is the most inconsiderable part of the universe.2 That is because Newton admits 
empty space as well as matter, and holds that matter fills up only a very small 
part of space. But Democritus and Epicurus maintained the same thing, except that they may have 
believed there to be more matter in the world than Newton will allow; and as to that, I think their opinion is 
preferable to his, because the more matter there is the more opportunity God has to exercise his 
wisdom and power. And that is just one of  several reasons that I have for holding that there is no empty space at all. 
To Clarke's 3 <ref n="2"/>
		</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="11" ref="7">3 In the  Appendix to his Optics I find Newton saying explicitly that space is the 
sensorium of God; and ' sensorium' has always signified the organ of sensation. If he and his friends now see fit to 
mean something different by it, I shan 't object.</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="12" ref="7"> 4 Clarke supposes that the -mere- presence of the soul is 
sufficient to make it aware of what happens  in the brain. <!-- The verb phrase &apos;to be aware of&apos; translates s&apos;apercevoir 
de. Clarke always translates this by  &apos;perceive&apos;, but that is wrong. In these papers Leibniz hardly ever uses 
percevoir = &apos;perceive&apos;, and  not once does he speak of what God perceives. It is always what 
God &apos;senses&apos;, &apos;is  aware of&apos;, or (once) &apos;discerns&apos;. -->
			But this is just 
what Malebranche and all the Cartesians deny; and  they are right to do so. For x to represent what happens in y, mere presence isn't 
enough; there has to be something that explains  what x and y have to do with one another-either -one acts on the other, or -both are 
acted on by a single cause. -Of course mere presence  isn't enough-. According to Newton, -a region of- space is 
intimately present to the body that it contains and  that has the same shape and size as it does; would he infer from this that 
space is aware of what happens in a body and  remembers it when the body has moved on? -And when it comes to the presence of the 
			soul, the trouble is even worse-.  The soul is indivisible; -it has no size-; so if we try to tell a 
story about its 'presence' in the body, it  could be present only at a point; so how could it be aware of what happens outside that point? 
I claim to be the first person to show how  the soul becomes aware of what happens in the body. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="13" ref="7">5 The reason why 
			God is aware of everything is  not just his -presence but also his -activity; he preserves things by an 
action that continually produces whatever is good  and perfect in them, -and of course he is aware of what he is doing-. But
			 the correspondence between soul and body can't be -even partly- explained by their being present to each other, 
because neither of them has any immediate  influence over the other. To Clarke's 4 <ref n="2a3"/>
		</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="14" ref="8">6 When we commend a machine, that 
is primarily because of what -it does, not  because of what -caused it; and what this reflects in the designer of the machine is his 
-skill, not his -power. So the reason Clarke  gives for praising God's Actually, he says that 'mathematical
			 principles' have that  consequence, but it's really Newton's system that he is talking about. 
Mathematical  principles, -properly so-called-, have nothing to say about this. machine-namely, that he made it entirely, 
without bringing in any  materials from outside-isn't good enough. How does God surpass every other machine-maker? 
Well, -Clarke's  reason is a part of the story-: God makes the whole thing, whereas others have to be given materials 
to work upon; so  he surpasses them in -power. But
			God's excellence also has another source, namely his 
-wisdom,  which shows in his machine's lasting longer and moving more regularly than machines made by anyone else. When you buy a watch 
you don 't care whether the watchmaker made every part of it himself or got the parts from elsewhere and merely assembled them to make 
the  watch-provided the watch goes right! Even if the workman had a God-given ability to create the matter
			that the wheels are made of, what you as the buyer of the watch will want to know is whether he had a different God
			-given ability, namely the gift of assembling the parts to make a watch that runs properly! Similarly, someone looking for 
reasons to be  pleased with God's work will want a better reason than the one that Clarke has produced. His supposed 
reason is  really just a dodge that he was forced into -by his refusal to credit God's machine with 
the  absolute regularity that is its chief glory-. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="15" ref="8">7 God's skill has to be infinitely superior to that of a 
-human-  workman. The mere facts about what he produces do show God's power, but don't adequately  
convey his wisdom. Those who think otherwise-acknowledging the power but not properly admitting the wisdom of the source  
of things-will fall into exactly the same error as the materialists and Spinoza, though they try to keep them at arms' length. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="16" ref="8">8 I 
'm not saying that the material world is a machine (a watch, say) that runs without God's intervening, and I  have 
pretty strongly insisted that the things he has created need his continual influence. But I do say that the material  
world is a watch that runs without needing to be mended by God; otherwise we would have to say that God
			 changes his mind! -In fact-, God has foreseen everything; and for anything that might go wrong he has  
provided a remedy in advance. There is in his works a harmony, a pre-established beauty. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="17" ref="8">9 This opinion doesn't exclude God
			's providence or his government of the world; on the contrary, it makes it perfect. A true divine providence requires  perfect 
foresight-and also provision in advance for any remedies that will turn out to be needed. Otherwise God must be  
lacking either in the wisdom to foresee things or the power to provide for them in advance. He'll be like the God  of 
the Socinians <!-- fore-runners of the unitarians --> , who 'takes each day as it comes', as Jurieu says. In fact the  Socinians' 
God doesn't even -foresee things' going wrong, whereas the Newtonians I am arguing with say  only that he doesn't -provide 
against them, and so has to fix them as they occur. Even this strikes me as a great lack; it implies  that God is 
lacking either in power or in good will. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="18" ref="8"> 10 I don't see anything wrong with my saying that God is intelligentia 
supramundana <!-- 4 on page 2 --> . Will those who criticize this say that he is intelligentia mundana <!-- =  &apos;a thinking being who 
is in (or of) the world&apos; --> , i.e. the soul of the world? I hope not! But they had better watch 
out that they don't carelessly end up in that position. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="19" ref="8"> 11 Clarke's example of a kingdom in which  everything goes well without 
the king's getting involved in any way is irrelevant to our present topic; because Godcontinually preserves everything 
and nothing can exist without him. His kingdom is not a kingdom in name only and not in reality! Another  example: A king takes care to 
have his subjects well brought up, providing for their needs so that they keep their abilities and good  dispositions-doing this so 
thoroughly that he never needs to fix anything that has gone wrong. Is he 'a king only in name'? </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="20" ref="8">12 A  final point: If God
			 has to mend the course of nature from time to time, he must do it 
either -supernaturally or -naturally. If -supernaturally, this is appealing to miracles in order to explain  natural things; and that 
amounts to a reductio ad absurdum of this hypothesis <!-- i.e. it refutes the hypothesis by showing that  something absurd follows from it 
--> , for once you let in miracles anything can be 'explained' with no trouble at all. And if God's mending is done 
-naturally, then rather than being intelligentia supramundana he is included in the nature of things-i.e. is the 
			soul of the world.</Utterance>
	</Turn>
	<Turn nickname="Clarke" nr="2">Clarke's second reply (10 January 1716)  <Utterance genid="21" ref="9">1 <page n="3"/>
 When I said that the mathematical principles of philosophy are opposite to those of the materialists, I  meant this 
contrast: -Materialists think that the whole order of nature could have arisen from mere mechanical  principles of 
			matter and motion, acting -blindly and -inevitably. -The mathematical principles of  philosophy show 
that, on the contrary, the state of things (the constitution of the sun and planets) must have had a cause that was acting  -thoughtfully 
and -freely. As for what the principles in question should be called: to the extent that metaphysical consequences follow  rigorously from 
			mathematical ones, to that extent one could call the mathematical principles ' metaphysical', if one 
wanted to. It is very true that nothing exists without there being a sufficient reason why it exists why it is  thus rather than so. So 
where there is no cause, there can be no effect. But often this sufficient reason is simply the  will of God
			. <!-- NB: Now comes the kick-off for what will be the most famous topic of this exchange. --> For an  example, consider two 
material things (particles or complexes) that are exactly alike and are -of course- in different places. Why are  they situated as they 
are rather than the other way around? Why is x here and y there, rather than y here and x there? So far as bits of matter
			 are concerned, one place is the same as another, so that if the locations of x and y had been switched it would  have been 
exactly the same thing <!-- the italicised words are exactly Clarke&apos;s --> . So the only reason there can be for the two  things to be 
where they are rather than vice versa is the mere will of God. If God couldn't  choose without a 
predetermining cause, any more than a balance can move without an imbalance of weights, this would tend to take away all  power of 
choosing, and to introduce fatality. <!-- We&apos;ll find that &apos;fatality&apos; is a hard word to pin down. It connects with  
&apos;fate&apos;, whose Latin root connects-as Leibniz will point out later-with &apos;decree&apos;. Its broad meaning is: the thesis 
that  whatever happens was inevitable, &apos;fated&apos; to happen. -->
		</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="22" ref="10">2 <ref n="4"/> Many ancient Greeks, who derived their 
philosophy from  the Phoenicians and had it corrupted by Epicurus, did indeed believe in matter and vacuum; 
but they  -were unlike Newton in a way that Leibniz doesn't mention, namely they- didn't know how put mathematics 
to  work in using those matter-and-vacuum principles to explain the phenomena of nature. -As for 
the  question of how much matter we should think there is-: Even if there isn't much matter, that  
doesn't reduce God's scope for exercising his wisdom and power, because he can act wisely and powerfully on  things 
other than matter. Re-applying Leibniz's amount-of-matter argument, we could say that  there must be 
infinitely many men (and infinitely many dogs, horses, lions etc.), so as to give God enough scope for  the full 
exercise of his power and wisdom. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="23" ref="11">3 <ref n="4"/> The word 'sensorium', used properly, refers not to the organ of  sensation 
but to the place of sensation. The eye, the ear etc. are organs, but not sensoria <!-- = plural  of sensorium 
--> . Besides, Newton doesn't say that space is the sensorium -of God-. He merely  offers a 
comparison, saying that space is as it were the sensorium etc. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="24" ref="12">4 <ref n="4"/> It was never supposed that the  
presence of the soul was -sufficient for perception to occur, only that it is -necessary for it. If it weren't  present 
to the images of the things perceived, the soul couldn't possibly perceive them: but being  present 
isn't enough for perception, because only a living substance can have a perception. A present inanimate substance doesn' t perceive 
anything; and a living substance can perceive things only if it is present to -the things themselves (as the omnipresent God
			 is to the whole universe) or present to -the images of the things (as the soul of man is in its  own 
sensorium). Nothing can act or be acted on where it isn't present, just as nothing can exist where it isn't -present-! The soul
			's being indivisible doesn't imply that it can be present only at a mere point. Space-finite or infinite-is 
absolutely indivisible. It isn't even conceptually divisible; to imagine parts of space  moving away from one another 
is to imagine them, as Newton has remarked, moved out of themselves! Yet space is not a  mere point. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="25" ref="13">5 <ref n=
"c4"/>
			God perceives things, not indeed by -being merely present to them or by -acting on them, but by 
-being a living, thinking thing as well as an omnipresent one. Similarly with the -human- soul: it  perceives things 
(vastly fewer than God perceives) by perceiving images of them; and it perceives those not by being  merely present to 
them but by being a living substance. Without being present to them it couldn't perceive them, but (I 
repeat) mere presence isn't enough. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="26" ref="14">6 and </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="27" ref="14">7 <ref n="5"/> It's very true that the excellence of God's 
workmanship consists in its manifesting not only his power but also his wisdom. But what  shows his wisdom 
is his forming at the outset the perfect and complete idea of a work that began and still carries on in conformity with  that perfect 
idea, doing this through the continual uninterrupted exercise of God's power and government. It is  not shown by his 
making nature capable of going on without him (like someone making a clock); because that's  impossible. The powers of 
a clock's weights and springs don't depend on men, -which is why a man can make a clock that will  continue to run without him-. 
But there are no powers of nature that are independent of God, -which is why 
nature can't possibly continue to run without him-. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="28" ref="16">8 <ref n="5"/> The words ' correction' and 'amendment' are to be 
understood -in the present context- in terms of our minds, not in terms of God's. For example: the present set-up of 
the solar system, according to the present laws of motion, will in time fall into confusion; and after that it may be 
'amended' or put into a new form. But this ' amendment' is relative to our conceptions--in performing it (if he does), 
			God will be taking something that -is  confusing us, and making it -easier for us to understand; he won't be taking 
something that -has gone wrong, and -fixing it-. In  reality, and from God's standpoint, the present set-up and the 
consequent disorder and the ensuing 'amendment ' are all equally parts of the design embodied in the perfect idea that God
			 had from the outset. -As for  longevity-: With the whole universe, as with any individual human body, God's 
wisdom consists not in making it  eternal but in making it last as long as he sees fit. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="29" ref="17">9 <ref n="5"/>
			God
			's wisdom and foresight don 't consist in his providing from the outset remedies that will automatically cure the disorders of 
			nature.  Strictly speaking, from God's standpoint there aren't any disorders, so there aren't any 
remedies  either; nor are there any powers of nature that can do things unaided (as weights and springs work unaided by 
men). God's wisdom and foresight (I repeat) consist in his forming all at once a design that his power and government 
is  continually carrying out. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="30" ref="18">10 <ref n="5"/>
			God is neither a mundane intelligence, nor a supra-mundane 
intelligence. He  is an omnipresent intelligence, both inside the world and outside of it. He is in all, and through all, as well as being 
above all. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="31" ref="19">11 <ref n="5"/> -Leibniz agrees that God continually preserves things, but what does 
that mean-? If God's conserving -or preserving- all things means his being actually at work preserving and continuing 
the beings, powers,  orders, dispositions and motions of all things, -that is all I am arguing for. But if God
			's  conserving things means merely a king's creating subjects who will be able to act well enough, for ever after, without his  
interfering or giving them any orders, -this does indeed make him a real creator, but a 'governor' in name only.  </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="32" ref="20">
12 <ref n="6"/> Leibniz's argument in this paragraph presupposes that everything that God does is supernatural or  
miraculous; so what it's aiming at is to exclude all activity by God in governing and ordering the natural world.  In 
fact, though, the distinction between 'natural' and 'supernatural' doesn't exist from God's standpoint; all it marks is 
a difference between two ways that we have of thinking about things. Causing the sun or the earth to  move regularly is something we call 
'natural': stopping its motion for a day we would call 'supernatural'; but neither of these needs more power than the 
other, and from God's standpoint neither is more or less  natural or supernatural than the other. God
's being present in the world, or to the world, doesn't make him  the soul of the world.3 A soul is 
part of a compound, the other part being a body, and they affect  each other as parts of the same whole. But
			God
			 is present to the world not as a -part but as -a governor; acting on everything and not acted on by anything. 
He is not far from every one of us, for in him we and all things  live and move and have our beings. 'God governs all 
things, not as a soul of the world but as the lord of the universe. . . "God" is a 
relative word, carrying in its meaning the idea of  relation to servants. And God's divinity is his dominion <!-- = 
&quot;command&quot; --> -not like the soul's command over the body, but that of a lord over his 
servants. . . . In God all things  exist and move in him, but without interacting with him: the 
movements of bodies have no effect on God,  and when they move they aren't obstructed by God's 
omnipresence. . . . He is entirely without body or bodily  shape, so he can't be seen or heard or felt; and he ought not to be worshipped 
through the representation of any physical thing. We  have ideas of his -attributes, but we don't know 
what the -substance is of any thing. . . .'  Newton, Principia, General Scholium. </Utterance>
	</Turn>
	<Turn nickname="Leibniz" nr="3">Leibniz's third 
paper (25 February 1716) <Utterance genid="33" ref="21">To Clarke's 1 <page n="6"/>
		1 In  the usual sense of the phrase, 'mathematical 
principles' concern only pure mathematics-i.e. numbers and figures, arithmetic and geometry. Whereas 'metaphysical' 
principles concern more general notions, such as  cause and effect. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="34" ref="21">2 Clarke grants me this important principle, that nothing 
happens without a sufficient reason why it should be so rather  than otherwise. But he grants it only in words and in 
reality denies it. This shows that he hasn't properly  understood the strength of it. That leads him to use as an example something that 
exactly fits one of my demonstrations against -real  absolute space, -the idol of some modern Englishmen -including 
Newton and Clarke-. (I'm not using 'idol'  in a theological way, but in a philosophical sense, following Bacon's thesis 
that there are idols of the tribe and  idols of the cave, -and so on-.)
 <!-- Let&apos;s get this clear: Leibniz knows that Clarke follows 
Newton in -accepting &apos;real  absolute space&apos;, says that Clarke&apos;s &apos;Why-are-they-this-way-round?&apos; 
argument is really part of  Leibniz&apos;s case -against real absolute space, and offers this as evidence that Clarke 
doesn&apos;t have a proper  grasp of the issues.-As for the unexplained phrase &apos;real absolute space&apos;: 
you&apos;ll do best to hold it in  mind and let its meaning grow out of the debate surrounding it. -->
		</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="35" ref="21">3 So there we are: these 
gentlemen maintain that space is a real absolute being, which leads them into great difficulties. -Here is just one-. 
It seems that if there is such a being  as real absolute space, it must be eternal and infinite. That's why some people 
have believed that space is God himself, or one of his attributes-namely the attribute of immensity. But
			space doesn't fit with God, because space
			 has parts. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="36" ref="21">4  For my part, I have said several times that I hold space to be 
something merely relative, as time is, taking space to be an order of coexistences, as time
			 is an order of  successions. For space indicates. . . an order of things existing at the same time
			, considered just  as existing together, without bringing in any details about what they are like. When we see a number of 
things together, one becomes aware  of this order among them. <!-- Leibniz says that space indicates en termes de possibilite-&apos;in terms of  possibility&apos;-an order of things etc. Meaning? -->
		</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="37" ref="21">5 As for those who imagine that space
			 is a substance, or at  least that it is something absolute, I have many demonstrations to show them to be wrong. But
			 just now I'll use only  one of these-the one that Clarke has opened the door to -in the section of his paper that I am discussing-. 
The demonstration argues that  if space were an absolute being, something would be the case for which there couldn't 
possibly be a sufficient  reason-which conflicts with my axiom, -and thus implies that space is not an absolute being-. 
Here's how the  argument goes: (1) Space is something absolutely uniform; one point of space doesn't 
differ in  any way from any other point of space. (I mean that it doesn't differ absolutely, i.e. apart from 
differences in  what bodies there are at the two places.) Add to that the thesis that I am arguing against: (2) Space 
is something in  itself, besides the order of bodies among themselves; -i.e. space is absolutely real-. From (1) and 
(2) it follows that  (3) God could not possibly have had a reason for putting the material universe in space
			 in this way  -rather than in some other way that retained the same spatial relations of bodies to one another -e.g. -rather 
than rotating the world so  as to switch west to east. -That would conflict with the principle of sufficient reason; so it can't happen; 
so premise (2) is  false-Q.e.d.- But if we replace (2) by (2*) Space is nothing but an 
order or set of  relations among bodies, so that in the absence of bodies space is nothing at all except the 
possibility of placing  them, then we don't get the conclusion (3), because the supposed two states--the universe where it is and -the 
universe rotated  through 180 degrees-are not two states, but one; they are la m^eme chose, the same thing. We have the 
illusion of  difference, coming from the fanciful supposition that space is a real independent entity; but
			 in  reality the -supposed- two states are indistinguishable, so they are really one; so the question 'Why did God  
choose this one rather than that?' doesn't arise. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="38" ref="21">6 The same thing holds for time. Suppose someone -asks  'Why 
didn't God did create everything a year sooner than he did?', -sees that this has no answer, and  -infers that 
God has made a choice where there couldn't possibly be a reason for his choosing that way rather than  some other. I say that 
his inference would be right if time was some thing distinct from things existing in time -or events 
occurring in time-; for in that case it would indeed be impossible for there to be any reason  why events shouldn't 
have occurred in exactly the order they did but at some different time. But what that 
argument really proves is that times, considered without the things -or events-, are nothing  at all, and that they 
consist only in the successive order of things -and events-. On that view of what time is, the  supposed 'two states of 
affairs'--the world exactly as it is, and -the world as it is except for having started a year sooner  -don't differ at all, are 
indiscernible, are really just one. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="39" ref="21">7 It can be seen from all this that Clarke hasn't properly  understood my axiom, which he 
rejects even while seeming to accept it. It's true, he says, that for any state of affairs there is a  sufficient reason why it is so 
rather than otherwise, but he adds that this 'sufficient reason' is often simply  the mere will of God. 
And he gives the example of the world's being located in space as it is  rather than as it would be if it were rotated 
through 180 degrees. But this clearly involves saying that something does  happen without any sufficient reason for it, 
namely God's making that choice; which conflicts with the axiom or  general rule about everything that is the case. 
This involves sliding back into the loose indifference--the tolerance for the idea of  choice in the absence of any reason for choosing 
one way rather than another--a view that I have abundantly refuted, showing it to be  utterly fictional even as applied to creatures, and 
to be contrary to the wisdom of God because it implies that he  could act without acting by reason. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="40" ref="21">8 Clarke 
objects against me that if we don't admit this simple and mere will, we deprive God of the power of choosing and bring 
in a fatality <!-- see note on page 6 --> . But the exact opposite is  true! I maintain that God has 
the power of choosing, a power that is based on his having, in his wisdom, reasons for  his choices. This 'fatality' is nothing but the way the universe has been ordered by providence, -by God-, the wisest being; what has to be avoided is not 
that, but a blind fatality, a necessity that has no wisdom or  choice in it. To Clarke's 2 </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="41" ref="22">
			<ref n="6"/> 9 I had 
remarked that a lessening of the amount of matter would lessen  the quantity of objects that God 
could exercise his goodness on. Clarke answers that in the space  where there's no matter there are 
other things on which God exercises his goodness. I don' t agree, because I hold every created substance is accompanied 
by matter; but let that pass, -because  even if Clarke were right about that, it wouldn't answer the 
point I had been making-. If there were space that  was empty of matter
			but full of 
those 'other things’, more matter could  also have been present in that space; and so its not being 
there means a lessening in the number of objects God has to work with. The quip about -my implying that there ought to 
be- a greater number of men or animals misses its target,  because more men or animals would fill places that could be occupied by other 
things. To Clarke's 3 </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="42" ref="23">
			<ref n="7"/> 10 It will be hard  to convince me that 'sensorium' in its usual meaning doesn't signify an 
organ of sensation. See what Goclenius says about  the word in his philosophical dictionary. He calls it 'a barbarism used by some 
scholastics aping the Greeks', and equates it  with 'organ of sensation' <!-- Leibniz quotes the passage in Latin --> . To Clarke's 4
		</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="43" ref="24">
			<ref n="7"/> 11 The mere presence of  a substance, even an animated one, is not sufficient for perception. A blind man, and even 
someone whose thoughts are wandering, doesn 't see. Clarke should explain how the soul is aware of things outside 
itself. To Clarke's 5 </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="44" ref="25">
			<ref n="7"/> 12 God is present to things not by situation but by essence; 
his presence shows in his immediate  operation. <!-- This sentence seems to rest on the idea that God&apos;s essence is 
his power. So the thought is that  -God is present to everything not because he is everywhere but 
because his essence = power is  everywhere; which goes with the thought that -God is present in a place not because he 
is there but  because he acts there. We&apos;ll see in Clarke&apos;s 12 <ref n="14"/> that that&apos;s how he understands 
the passage. --> The presence  of the soul is something else again. If we say 'It is spread all through the body', we 
make it extended and  divisible. If we say 'It-the whole of it-is in every part of the body', we divide it from itself. All this talk 
about ' fixing the soul to a point', 'spreading the soul across many points'-it's just  gabble, 
idols of the tribe! </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="45" ref="27">To Clarke's 6-7
			<ref n="7"/> 13 If the universe lost some of its active force by the  
natural laws God has established, so that -later on- there was a need for him to give it a shove in order to restore  
that force (like an artisan repairing his machine), this would involve something's going 'wrong' not  only from our 
standpoint but also from God's. He could have prevented it by having a better plan  in the first 
place-which is of course exactly what he did! To Clarke's 8 and 9 </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="46" ref="28">
			<ref n="7"/> 14 When I said that Godhas 
provided remedies for such disorders in advance, I wasn't saying that God lets the disorders occur and then  finds 
remedies for them, but that he has found a way of preventing any disorders in the first place. To Clarke's 10</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="47" ref="30">
			<ref n="8"/> 15 Clarke isn't getting anywhere with his criticism of my statement that God is intelligentia  supramundana. 
Saying that God is -above the world isn't denying that he is -in the world. To Clarke's 11 </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="48" ref="31">
			<ref n="8"/> 16 I 
never gave any occasion to question that God's conservation is an actual preservation and  continuation of the beings, 
powers, orders, dispositions, and motions -of all things-, and I think I may have explained this better than  many others have. But, says Clarke, 'that is all I am arguing for'. Well, what a relief! But in  fact there is much more than that to 
our dispute. The questions -Does God act in the most regular and most perfect  manner? -Could his machine develop a 
fault that he would have to repair by extraordinary means? -Can God's will  act without reason? -Is space
			 is an absolute being? -What are miracles? and many others like them make a wide  difference between us. To Clarke's 12 
		</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="49" ref="32">
			<ref n="8"/> 17 Theologians won't agree with Clarke (against me) that from God's standpoint there is no 
distinction between 'natural' and 'supernatural'; and most philosophers will  disagree with him even more strongly. There is an infinite 
difference between these two, but evidently Clarke hasn't  thought hard about this. The supernatural exceeds all the 
powers of created things. Here's a good example that I have used before: If God wanted to bring this about - a body 
moves freely through the ether around a certain fixed centre, without any other  created thing acting on it - I say that this couldn't be 
done without a miracle, because it can't be explained by the nature of bodies. What a free body moving along a curve 
would naturally do -at any given moment- is to move away from the curve  along the -straightline- tangent to it. That's why I contend that 
the attraction of bodies, properly so called, is a miraculous  thing-i.e. because it can't be explained by the nature 
of bodies. </Utterance>
	</Turn>
	<Turn nickname="Clarke" nr="3">Clarke's third reply (15  May 1716) <Utterance genid="50" ref="33"> 1<page n="9"/> This concerns only the meaning 
of words. We can accept Leibniz's definitions of 'mathematical' and 'metaphysical'; but -the fact 
remains that- mathematical reasonings can  be applied to physical and metaphysical subjects. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="51" ref="34">2 <ref n="9"/> For 
anything that exists, there is a sufficient reason why it exists, and  why it is thus rather than so-there's no doubt about that. Clarke 
writes next: : But in things in their own nature indifferent, mere will, without any thing external to 
influence it, is alone that sufficient reason. informally  expressed: But when there are two options neither of which is 
intrinsically better than the other, the sufficient reason  for someone's choosing option x rather than option y may be just that he 
chooses x, without being caused by anything else to do so. <!-- The above &apos;informal expression&apos; serves to explain the word 
&apos;indifferent&apos;, which here makes its first appearance  in this text, and will occur many times hereafter. --> 
An example of this is God's creating or  placing a particle of matter in one place rather than in 
another, when all places are in themselves alike. And this  example would still work even if space were not something 
real but only the mere order of bodies: for  even then, it would be absolutely indifferent, and there could be no reason 
except mere will, why three equal particles should be placed  in the order a-b-c rather than in the contrary order. So this point about 
the indifferentness of all places doesn't generate an  argument showing that no space is real; because two regions of 
			space that are perfectly alike are  still -really different or distinct one from another, -even if they are not in 
themselves real things-. <!-- This paragraph is aimed at  Leibniz&apos;s 5 <page n="9"/>. --> The thesis that space is 
not a real thing but merely the order of  bodies is obviously absurd -in a way that I didn't point out earlier-. According 
to this thesis, if the solar system had been placed  where the remotest fixed stars now are, with all relationships of order and distance 
exactly what they are in fact, -this would indeed  have been (as Leibniz rightly says) la m^eme chose, the same thing in effect; -
but it would also imply that the solar  system would have been exactly where it is now, which is an explicit contradiction. 
			<!-- Leibniz&apos;s la m^eme chose does indeed mean  &apos;the same thing&apos;. Adding &apos;in effect&apos; weakens the phrase; that was 
Clarke&apos;s work, with no basis in Leibniz&apos;s  text. -->
			<!-- Clarke says that this paragraph responds to something Leibniz said in a 
private letter (we don&apos;t now have it). --> The  ancients didn't give the label 'imaginary space’ to all 
space that is empty of  bodies, but only space that is outside the -material- world. And they 
didn't mean that such space is not real,4 but only that we know nothing of what kinds of things are in 
it. And if anyone did  ever call space 'imaginary', meaning by this that it isn't real, that's no argument that it isn 
't real! </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="52" ref="35">3 <ref n="9"/>
			Space is not a being -or thing-, an eternal and infinite being -or thing-. Rather, it is 
a  property-something that depends on the existence of a being that is infinite and eternal. Infinite space is 
immensity. <!-- The term &apos;immensity&apos;, which we will meet often, means &apos;infinite largeness&apos;. It relates to 
space as eternity relates to time (if we understand eternity to be existence through an infinitely  
long stretch of time; not everyone does, because some think of eternity as timeless, but we can see from Clarke&apos;s 4 on page 2 that he isn&apos;t one of them). -->
			But immensity is not 
			God; so infinite space is not God. As for Leibniz's point about space
			 having parts: there's no problem there, for the following reason. Infinite space is one, and is  absolutely 
and essentially indivisible; it's a contradiction to think of it as being parted. what Clarke wrote: because there must be space
			 in the partition itself; which is to suppose it parted and yet not parted at the same time.  what he may 
have meant: because any partition of space1 would have to take place in space2, meaning  that 
			space is (1) parted and yet (2) not parted at the same time. (See my 4 on page 7) God
			's immensity or omnipresence doesn't imply that his substance is divisible into parts, any more than his existing  through 
			time implies that his existence is divisible into parts. The only problem here arises from misusing the word  'parts' 
by not giving it its literal meaning. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="53" ref="36">4 <ref n="9"/> If space was nothing but the  order of 
coexisting things, it would follow that if God moved the entire material world in a straight line, it would  remain in 
the same place; and that however fast he moved it, and however abruptly he stopped it moving, nothing would be jolted. And if time
			 was nothing but the order of succession of created things, it would follow that if God had 
created the world millions of ages sooner than he did, it wouldn't have been created sooner at all. And Nothing doesn 't have any 
dimensions, magnitudes, quantity, properties. -Space outside the world has all those, so obviously it  isn't nothing, 
which is to say that it is real-. another point: space and time are quantities,  while situation and 
order are not. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="54" ref="37">5, </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="55" ref="38">6 <ref n="9"/> Leibniz argues like this: Space is uniform, with no part differing  from 
any other. Therefore, if the bodies that were created in place A had been created in place B instead (with the spatial relations  amongst 
them kept the same), then they would still have been created in place A, which is a manifest contradiction! The uniformity of 
space does indeed prove that God couldn't have an external reason for creating things in one  place rather 
than in another; but does that stop his own will from being in itself a sufficient reason for putting things  where he did 
put them, when all places are indifferent or alike, and there is good reason to put things somewhere? <!-- Notice that Clarke  has here 
started to expound an argument of Leibniz&apos;s and then switched it to one of his own (&apos;which is a manifest  contradiction&apos;). 
He does then answer Leibniz&apos;s actual argument (about sufficient reasons), but without having  stated it first. --> 
		</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="56" ref="39">7,</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="57" ref="40"> 8 <ref n="10"/> An intelligent and perfectly wise agent will always base his choices on any real differences there  are 
between the options confronting him. But how will such an agent act in a case-like the location-of-matter
			 example we have been discussing-where two ways of acting are equally good? To say that in such a case -God  
can't act at all; and -if he could act, that would be an imperfection in him, because he wouldn't have any external reason to  move him to 
act in one way rather than the other seems to deny that God has in himself any originating -energy-source  or -power of 
beginning to act, and to maintain that he always needs (mechanically, as it were) to be pushed into acting -or deciding- by  some external 
cause. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="58" ref="41">9 <ref n="10"/> I presume that the exact amount of matter that the world now contains is what' s best for 
the present frame of nature, or the present state of things; and that the state of the world would have been  less 
satisfactory if the amount of matter had been greater (or less). So it's not true that having more matter
			 would have provided a greater object for God to exercise his goodness on. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="59" ref="42">10 <ref n="11"/> The  
question is not what Goclenius means by 'sensorium', but what Newton means by it. . . . If Goclenius takes the  eye or ear 
or any other organ of sensation to be the sensorium, he is certainly mistaken. But -that's irrelevant to  our issue-. When 
a writer explicitly states what he means by any technical term, what's the point of asking what other meanings other  writers may have 
given it. Scapula in his dictionary translates it as domicilium, the place where the mind resides. <!-- Actually,  Scapula&apos;s entry 
for sensorium reads (in Latin): &apos;instrument of sensation; sometimes: place where the sense  resides&apos;. -->
		</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="60" ref="43"> 11 <ref n="11"/> The reason why the soul of a blind man doesn't see is that some obstruction  prevents images 
from being conveyed to the sensorium where the soul is present. We don't know how the soul of a 
sighted man sees the images that are present to it; but we are sure that it can't perceive what is  not present to it, 
because nothing can act or be acted upon in a place where it isn't!</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="61" ref="44"> 12 <ref n="11"/>
			God, being  omnipresent, is 
really present to everything both essentially and substantially. It's true that his presence at a place shows itself  by what he does 
there, but he can't act there unless he is there.5 The soul is not omnipresent to  every part of the 
body; so it doesn't and can't In a footnote Clarke quotes Newton in Latin, which he then translates as: God is 
omnipresent, not only virtually but substantially; for a power can't exist without a  substance -that has it-. itself act 
directly on every part of the body, but only on the brain and certain nerves and  spirits. These influence the whole body, 
by virtue of laws and causal connections that God has appointed. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="62" ref="45">13,</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="63" ref="46"> 14 <ref n="11"/> The fact that the 
active forces6 in the universe grow less and so need new input -to keep up their level- is not  an inconvenience, a 
disorder, an imperfection in the workmanship of the universe; it's simply a consequence of the nature of dependent 
things. And the dependency of things is not something that needs to be fixed! The case of a human workman making a  machine is quite 
different, because the powers or forces by which the machine continues to move are entirely  independent of the 
workman. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="64" ref="47">15 <ref n="11"/> The phrase intelligentia supramundana is quite all right when explained in Leibniz's  way. But
			 without this explanation the phrase is very likely to lead to the wrong idea that God is not  really and 
substantially present everywhere. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="65" ref="48">16 <ref n="11"/> Here are my answers to the questions that Leibniz raises in his 16 :  Leibniz: 
Does God act in the most regular and most perfect manner? Clarke: Yes. Leibniz: Could his machine develop a  fault that 
he would have to repair by extraordinary means? Clarke: There are no faults in anything God makes; and when  he chooses 
to alter the way things are going, this is no more 'extraordinary' than his choosing to keep them going in an  unaltered way. Leibniz: Can 
			God's will act without reason? Clarke: As between two options that are in their own nature 
absolutely equal and indifferent, God's will can freely choose -one of them-,  determining itself and not being acted 
on by any external cause; and his ability to do this is a perfection in him. Leibniz: Is space is an absolute being? 
Clarke: Space doesn't depend at all on the order or situation or existence  of bodies. Leibniz: What are miracles? 
Clarke: See the next section.</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="66" ref="49"> 17 <ref n="12"/> We haven't been discussing the question of what  will be accepted by theologians and 
philosophers; our topic has been the reasons men give for their opinions! If a miracle is simply  -something that exceeds the power of all 
created things, then it doesn't take a miracle for a man to walk on the water, or for the  motion of the sun or the earth to be stopped; 
because none of these things requires infinite power to bring it about. As for -Leibniz' s example of- a body in a vacuum circling around 
a central point: -there are two cases-. (1) If this is a -usual event (such as the  planets moving around the sun), it isn't a 
miracle-whether God brings it about immediately or indirectly through  some invisible created power. (2) If it's an 
-unusual event (such as a heavy body hanging in the air and moving in a circle), then it  is a miracle-whether God 
brings it about immediately or indirectly through some invisible created power. And a final  point: If we are to count as a miracle 
anything that doesn't arise from (and can't be explained in terms of) the natural powers  of body, then every animal motion whatsoever is 
a miracle. This seems to show conclusively that Leibniz's notion of a miracle is  erroneous. The phrase 'active force' 
in this context refers only to -motion and -the impetus or relative  impulsive force of bodies that arises from their 
motion and is proportional to it. That's because the discussion  of it that we have been having was prompted by this passage of Newton's: 
'It appears that motion may be got or lost. But because of the stickiness of fluids. . . and the weakness of elasticity in 
solids, motion is much more apt to be lost than got,  and is always decreasing. . . . Because the various kinds of motion that we find in 
the world are always decreasing, there is a need for  them to be conserved and augmented by active sources.'</Utterance>
	</Turn>
	<Turn author="Leibniz" nr="4">Leibniz's fourth paper (2 June 1716) 
	<Utterance genid="67" ref="51">To Clarke's 2 <page n="12"/> 1 When two options are absolutely 
indifferent--meaning that there's nothing to choose between them--there is no  choice, and consequently no election or will, since choice 
must be based on some reason or principle.</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="68" ref="51">2 A simple act of will without any  motive ('a mere will') is a fiction. It is -contrary to 
			God's perfection, -chimerical and contradictory,  -inconsistent with the definition of will, and -sufficiently confuted 
in my Theodicy.</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="69" ref="51"> 3 Regarding the order in which to place three equal  and perfectly alike particles-that's a case of indifferent 
options, and consequently they will never be placed in any order by God, who does nothing without wisdom--and there 
couldn't be any wisdom in arbitrarily choosing one out of a set of  indifferent options-. But -this doesn't imply that in 
such cases God is stuck-. He is the author  of things--all things--and he doesn't ever produce such a thing as three 
indiscernible particles; so no such thing occurs in nature.</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="70" ref="51"> 4 There is no such thing as a pair of individuals 
that are indiscernible from each other. A lively-minded friend of  mine, discussing these matters with me in the 
presence of the Princess Sophia in the garden of Herrenhausen, thought he  could find two leaves perfectly alike. The princess challenged 
him to do it, and he spent ages running all over the garden look for such a  pair of leaves-without finding any. Two drops of water or 
milk will turn out to be distinguishable from each other when viewed with a  microscope. This is an argument against atoms, which are 
driven out -and empty space along with them-by the principles  of true metaphysics.</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="71" ref="51"> 5 The great principles of 
-sufficient reason and the -identity of indiscernibles change the status of metaphysics.  They make metaphysics real and demonstrative, 
whereas before it didn't amount to much more than empty words.</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="72" ref="51"> 6 'Suppose x and y  are two indiscernible things' comes down to 
'Suppose x is y, and that this thing has two names'. What does this imply about  the hypothesis that the universe could right from the 
outset have had a different spatial and temporal location from what it actually had,  with everything else about it-including the 
spatio-temporal inter-relations among parts of the universe-remaining actually the same? It  implies that the hypothesis is an impossible 
fiction.</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="73" ref="51"> 7 The reason why -space outside the world is imaginary is also  the reason why -all empty space
			 is an imaginary thing. The only difference between -space that has  the world nested within it and -any 
other stretch of space is that one is bigger than the other. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="74" ref="52">To Clarke's 3 <ref n="13"/> 8 If space
			 is a property or attribute, it must be the property of some substance. Well, what  about the bounded empty 
			space that the friends of empty space say occurs between any two bodies? Of  what substance will 
that space be a property?</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="75" ref="52"> 9 If infinite space -is immensity, finite space 
will be the opposite to immensity, i.e. will be -measurability, or -limited extension. Now extension must be a property of  something 
extended. But if the finite space we have been talking about is empty, it will be an attri
bute without a subject, an extension without anything extended. The upshot is that when Clarke makes space  a 
property, he falls in with my opinion, which makes it an order of things and not anything absolute. <!-- Leibniz is here arguing like  
this: In saying that space is a -property, Clarke at least firmly rules out space&apos;s being a  
thing; but given that there is often nothing for it to be a property of, he is left with &apos;not a thing&apos; and  
&apos;not a property&apos;, from which he should infer the Leibnizian conclusion &apos;therefore, a -relation&apos;. -->
		</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="76" ref="52"> 10 If 
			space is an absolute reality--i.e. a thing--it will be even more thing-like (i.e. have more reality) than substances 
themselves! God can't destroy it, or even change it in any respect. As well as being immense taken as a whole, it will 
be  unchangeable and eternal in every part. There will be an infinity of eternal things besides God. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="77" ref="52">11 To say 
that  infinite space has no parts is to say -that it isn't made up of finite spaces, and -that  
infinite space could continue to exist even if finite spaces were reduced to nothing. <!-- He adds 
a  comparison, to highlight the absurdity. -->
		</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="78" ref="52">12 In another of his writings <!-- Leibniz gives the reference --> Clarke attributes parts to space; but in his second paper he says they are parts improperly so 
called-which may be  understood in a good sense. <!-- Clarke doesn&apos;t say this in his second paper as we have it. -->
		</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="79" ref="53"> To 
Clarke's 4 <ref n="14"/> 13  To say that God can make the whole universe move in a straight line (or any other line!) 
without changing it in any  other way is another fantasy. For two states indiscernible from each other are the same state, so that this 
'movement of the entire  world along a straight line' is a change that doesn't change anything. Besides, there is neither rhyme nor reason 
in it; and God does nothing without reason, and it is impossible that there should be any here. . . . </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="80" ref="53">14 These 
are idols of the  tribe <!-- Bacon&apos;s phrase, see page 9 --> , mere chimeras, and superficial imaginations. The only basis for this is 
the supposition  that imaginary space is real. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="81" ref="53">15 The supposition that God might move the 
entire world is like the  fiction that he might have created the world some millions of years sooner-like it in being impossible! Anyone 
who buys into fictions of  that sort will have to go along with those who argue for the eternity of the world. -Here is why-. God
			 does nothing  without reason; no reason can be given why he didn't create the world sooner; so if he has indeed created the 
world, then he created  it before any assignable time--i.e. for any time t, he created it earlier 
than t because he had no  reason not to--which is to say that the world is eternal. But once it has been shown that the 
beginning, whenever it was,  is always the same thing, that puts an end to the question 'Why didn't it occur earlier?'. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="82" ref="55">To Clarke's 
5, 6 <ref n="14"/> 16 If space and time were anything absolute, i.e. if they were anything 
but  certain orders of things, then indeed my assertion would be a contradiction. But since it is not so, the 
hypothesis -that space and time are something absolute- is contradictory, i.e. an impossible 
fiction. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="83" ref="55">17 This pattern  of argument is often used in geometry: we suppose that some figure is greater than it really is, and go 
on from that to prove that it is  not greater. This is a contradiction all right, but the contradiction lies in the 
hypothesis-the initial premise about the  size of the figure-which turns out to be false for just that reason. <!-- Just to make sure that 
this is understood: Leibniz is referring  here to the perfectly valid argument-pattern in which one derives not-P from P, this being a 
proof of not-P. He will use this same  argument-form in 22 and 23 on this page, and will comment on it in 28 on page 32 -->
		</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="84" ref="57"> To 
Clarke's 7, 8 <ref n="14"/> 18 Because space is uniform, there can't be any external or internal reason <!-- Leibniz 
uses the English words --> by which  to -distinguish its parts from one another and -choose among them. For any external reason to 
distinguish them, it would have to be  grounded on some internal one; otherwise (-i.e. if we gave some purely external reason for choosing 
x rather than y-), we would either be  discerning something that is indiscernible or be choosing without discerning. A will without reason 
would be mere Epicurean chance. A God who acted by such a will would be a God only in name. Clarke 
got into these errors through not  taking care to avoid everything that detracts from the divine perfections.</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="85" ref="57"> 19 When two 
incompatible things are equally good, with neither  having any advantage over the other (whether intrinsically or through their 
combination with other things), God won 't produce either of them. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="86" ref="57">20 God is never determined 
by external things but always by what is in  himself, i.e. by what he knows in advance of anything's existing outside him.
		</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="87" ref="58"> To Clarke's 9 <ref n="14"/> 21 There can't  possibly be a reason why the quantity of matter -in the universe- 
should be limited; so it can't be limited. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="88" ref="58">22  And if we start with the supposition that the quantity of matter 
is somehow limited in some arbitrary way: It's  always possible for more matter to be added to this without lessening 
the perfection of the things that do already  exist; therefore more matter must always be added, according to the 
principle of the perfection of the divine  operations; -which means that our initial supposition of a limited amount of matter
			 must be false-.</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="89" ref="58"> 23 So it can't  be said that the present quantity of matter is the 'best for the 
present state of things'. Supposing it were:  it would follow that this present state or constitution of things wasn't the absolutely 
best, because it would be blocking God from using more matter. So it would have been better if he 
had chosen a different constitution of things,  one that was capable of something more, -namely the existence of more matter
			. From which it follows that our initial  supposition 'There's a finite amount of matter, which is best for 
the world's actual constitution'  must be false-.</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="90" ref="59"> To Clarke's 10 <ref n="14"/> 24 I'd like to see a passage from any philosopher 
who takes 'sensorium'  in any other sense than Goclenius does. -Clarke scolds me for bringing Goclenius into the discussion, 
but- I was right to  cite his Philosophical Dictionary, to show how 'sensorium' is usually understood. That's what dictionaries are 
for. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="91" ref="59">25 If  Scapula says that sensorium is the place where the mind resides, he means by it the organ of internal sensation; so he 
doesn't differ  from Goclenius.</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="92" ref="59"> 26 'Sensorium' has always signified the organ of sensation. The pineal gland would be, according to 
Descartes,  the sensorium in the sense that Clarke reports Scapula as giving it. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="93" ref="59">27 Crediting God with having a 
sensorium is just  about the worst thing one could say on this subject; it seems to imply that God is the soul
			 of the  world. As for what Newton says using this word: it will be hard to find any interpretation that justifies it.</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="94" ref="59"> 28 
The question is indeed  about Newton's sense for that word, not Goclenius's, Clarke shouldn't criticize me for quoting the Philosophical  
Dictionary, because the design of dictionaries is to show the use of words. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="95" ref="61">To Clarke's 11, 12 <ref n="14"/> 29 God
			is aware of things in himself. <!-- This doesn&apos;t mean that God is aware of things that are in himself; 
but rather that God&apos;s awareness of things is in some special way internal to him. -->
			
Space is the place of things and not the place of God's ideas. To put God's ideas  into 
			space, we'd have to regard space as something that unites God with  things, along 
the lines of the union of soul and body that some people believe in; and then we would be back to making God
			 the soul of the world. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="96" ref="61">30 Clarke also goes wrong when he compares God's  knowledge 
and operation with the knowledge and operation of souls. Souls know things because God
			 has put into them what Leibniz wrote next: un principe representatif de ce qui est hors d'elles. how Clarke  translated that: a 
principle representative of things without. what Leibniz was getting at: a generator of representations of things  outside them. 
But
			God knows things because he is continually producing them. <!-- Clarke reports  difficulty with this 
passage in his 30 on page 25. Both principe and &apos;principle&apos; could be used to mean &apos;source&apos; or  &apos;cause&apos; or 
&apos;generator&apos;, and Clarke had that usage in his own repertoire: see for example &apos;physical cause or  &apos; near the end of 
his discussion of Leibniz&apos;s 1-20 on page 50. -->
		</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="97" ref="61">31 In my view, all there is to the soul's acting on things 
is the fact that the body adapts itself to the soul's desires, by virtue of the harmony  that God 
has pre-established between them. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="98" ref="61">32 But those who fancy that the soul can  give a new 
force to the body, and that God gives new force to the world so as to  fix the flaws in 
his machine, make God too much like the soul by ascribing too much to the soul 
and too little to God. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="99" ref="61">33 Actually, God alone can give new force  to 
			nature, and he does it only supernaturally. If he needed to do it in the natural course of events, that would  because 
he had made a very imperfect work. He would then relate to the world in the way ignorant people think the soul  relates 
to the body. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="100" ref="61">34 Those who try to defend the vulgar opinion about the soul's influence over the body by  citing 
			God's operating on things outside himself are-again!-making God too much like the soul
			 of the world. Clarke's show of disapproval for my phrase intelligentia supramundana seems to tend that way. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="101" ref="61"> 35 The 
images that the soul immediately has are within it, but they -correspond to the images of the  body. 
The soul can be present to something only in an imperfect way, which can be explained only in terms of that  
-correspondence -between the soul's images and the bodily images-. <!-- The body&apos;s &apos;images&apos; are the  
items referred to in the note on 3 on page 2 as the &apos;material counterparts or underlays&apos; of mental images. -->
			But
			
			God's way of being present to something is perfect = complete, and is manifested by his operation.</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="102" ref="61"> 36 It 
was  wrong of Clarke in arguing against me to help himself to the view that the soul's presence in the body is  
connected with its influence over the body; for he knows that I reject that influence.</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="103" ref="61"> 37 It's no easier to make sense of the 
			soul's being diffused throughout the -brain than of its being diffused through the -entire body. The difference  
between those is only one of more and less.</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="104" ref="63"> To Clarke's 13, 14 <ref n="15"/> 38 Those who fancy that active force
s  automatically decrease in the world don't properly understand the chief laws of nature or the beauty of God
			's works.</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="105" ref="63"> 39 How are they going to show that this loss-of-force defect is a consequence of the  
dependence of things? -I now proceed to show the exact opposite!- </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="106" ref="63">40 When one of our machines is flawed and has to be fixed, the 
reason  this has happened is that the machine did not sufficiently depend on the man who made it--i.e. some of the machine's functioning 
was  not sufficiently in accordance with the maker's design-. So nature's dependence on God,  far 
from causing the flaw we have been discussing, is the reason why that flaw doesn't occur in nature. It's  because 
			nature is so dependent on--so much in accordance with the designs of--a workman who is too perfect to make a  work that 
needed to be mended. Every particular machine in nature is somewhat liable to go out of order; but not 
the entire universe, which can't diminish in perfection.</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="107" ref="65"> To Clarke's 16 <ref n="15"/> 41 Clarke contends that space
			 doesn't depend on the situation of bodies. I reply that it's true that space doesn't  depend on this or that 
particular spatial lay-out of bodies, but it is the order that makes it possible for bodies to be  situated, and by which 
they have a lay-out among themselves when they exist together, just as what Leibniz wrote: le temps est cet ordre  par rapport `a leur 
position successive. what that means: time is that order with respect to their successive position.  what he may have 
been getting at: time is the order that makes it possible for events to have a chronology among  themselves when they 
occur at different times. If there were no created things, space and time would 
only be in the ideas of God. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="108" ref="66">To Clarke's 17 <ref n="15"/> 42 Clarke seems to acknowledge here  that his notion 
of a miracle isn't the one that theologians and philosophers usually have. what Leibniz wrote next: Il me suffit  donc, que mes 
adversaires sont obliges de recourir a ce qu'on appelle miracle dans l'usage receu et qu'on tache d' eviter en philosophisant. how Clarke 
translated it: It is therefore sufficient for my purposes that my adversaries are obliged to have  recourse to what is commonly called a 
miracle. a bit clearer and fuller: I'm satisfied to see that my adversaries have to avail  themselves of the ordinary everyday notion of 
miracle-a notion that one tries to avoid in doing science. <!-- You&apos;ll see the point of  laying those out in that way when you look 
at Clarke&apos;s extremely odd comment on this in his 42 on page 26. As for  &apos;science&apos;: in Leibniz&apos;s 
time &apos;philosophy&apos; often referred to natural science as well as to what  you and I call 
&apos;philosophy&apos;; and this is one of the places where that is certainly the case. -->
		</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="109" ref="66"> 43 By altering the  -philosophically- 
accepted sense of 'miracle', I'm afraid Clarke will get stuck with an awkward consequence. The nature of a miracle 
doesn't have anything to do with usualness/unusualness; if it did, then monsters would be miracles. <!-- By &apos;monster&apos; Leibniz 
here means &apos;human or other animal that has from birth physical features making it strikingly and  disquietingly unlike most members 
of its species&apos;. -->
		</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="110" ref="66">44 There are miracles at a lower level, which an angel can perform-e.g. making  a man walk on water 
without sinking. But there are miracles that only God can perform, because they  exceed all natural 
powers. Creating and annihilating are miracles of this kind.</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="111" ref="66"> 45 It is also a supernatural thing that bodies should  attract one 
another at a distance without any intermediate means, and that a body should circulate without shooting off along a tangent,  though 
nothing hinders it from doing that. For these effects can't be explained by the nature of things. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="112" ref="66"> 46 What 's the 
problem about explaining the -motions of animals through natural forces? It is true that the -beginnings of  animals 
can't be explained in that way, any more than the beginning of the world can. P.S. All those who maintain that there is empty 
space are influenced more by imagination than by reason. When I was a boy, I also bought into the notion of the -void <!-- = 
&apos;empty space&apos; --> and -atoms, with which my imagination had a lovely time. Thinking  in 
those terms, we take our inquiries no further than -those two things; they (as it were) nail our thoughts to them; we think that we  have 
found the first elements of things, the rock bottom. We don't want nature to go any further, wanting it to be  finite, 
like our minds. But then reason straightened me out, and showed me that this was sheer ignorance of the greatness  and 
majesty of -God-, the author of things. In fact, the tiniest corpuscle is actually subdivided to infinity, and  
contains a world of further creatures that the universe would lack if that corpuscle were an atom. . . Similarly, to postulate stretches  
of empty space in nature is to ascribe to God a very imperfect work; it violates  
the great principle of the necessity for a sufficient reason -for anything that is the case-. Plenty of people have paid lip-service to  
that principle, but they haven't understood its true meaning; as I recently showed when I used the principle to show  
-something that those payers of lip-service would never have expected to arise from it, namely- that space is only an  
order of things, as time also is, and not an absolute being. Setting aside many other arguments that I have against 
the  void and atoms, I'll present here the ones that I base on (1) God's perfection and (2) the necessity for a  
sufficient reason. (1) I lay it down as a principle that God has actually given to each thing every perfection that he  
could give to it without detracting from its other perfections. Now suppose there is a wholly empty region of space. 
			God could have put matter into it without taking anything away from anything else; so he actually  
has put matter in that region. -And that was just some region taken at random; the proof holds for any region-; so we  
have the result that no region of space is completely empty; therefore the whole of space is full.  
The same argument proves that -there are no atoms, i.e. that- every corpuscle is subdivided. <!-- The argument would go: Suppose there is  
an atom. God could have made divisions without taking any perfection away from it or anything else; so he has done  
that; so etc. --> (2) Here is a second argument, based on the need for a sufficient reason. There can't possibly be any principle to  
settle what proportion of space should have matter in it. You might say that the right proportion 
is  half, i.e. that there should be exactly as much filled space as empty space; but 
			matter is more perfect than empty space, so reason requires that there should be more matter
			 than vacuum-as much more as matter merits being preferred to vacuum. (-If matter is much  
more perfect than vacuum, there should be much more filled space than empty space. If matter
			 is just a little more perfect than vacuum, there should be just a little more filled space than empty-. ) 
By  that reasoning, there should be no empty space at all, because the ratio of -perfection of matter
 to  -perfection of vacuum is the ratio of -something to -nothing. A similar argument holds against atoms: what reason can anyone give 
what nature should be limited in how finely it is subdivided? -And what principle could lay down how far down the  
subdivision should go?- Atoms and the void are fictions, purely arbitrary and unworthy of true philosophy. The reasons Clarke gives for  
empty space are mere sophisms.</Utterance>
	</Turn>
	<Turn nickname="Clarke" nr="4">Clarke's fourth reply (26 June 1716) <Utterance genid="113" ref="67">1, 2 
			<page n="16"/> This  notion leads to universal necessity and fate, by supposing that motives relate to the will of an intelligent agent in 
the same way that  weights relate to a balance (see Leibniz's 1 on page 4); so that a thinking agent can no more choose between two 
absolutely  indifferent options than a balance can move itself when the weights on both sides are equal. The two are not on a par, because 
of the  following difference between them. -A balance is not an agent, -i.e. doesn't act-, but is merely passive and acted 
on  by the weights; so that when the weights are equal there is nothing to move it. But -thinking beings are agents; they 
aren 't passive things that are moved by their motives as a balance is moved by weights; rather, they have active powers through which  
they move themselves, sometimes upon the view of strong motives, sometimes upon weak ones, and some
			times where things are absolutely indifferent. <!-- In that sentence, the phrase &apos;upon the view of&apos; is  
Clarke&apos;s. --> Where the options are indifferent, there may still be very good reason to act. Leibniz always supposes the contrary, 
on  principle; but he doesn't prove this, either from the nature of things or from the perfections of 
			God. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="114" ref="69">3, 4 <ref n="16"/> If this argument were right, it would prove that God did not and could 
not  possibly create any matter at all! For the perfectly solid parts of all matter, if you take 
them to  have the same shapes and sizes (which is always possible in supposition), are exactly alike; in which case it would be perfectly  
indifferent if any two of them switched locations; and that, according to Leibniz's argument, makes it impossible for God
			 to locate them in the places where he did actually locate them at the creation, because he could as easily have switched their  
locations. Of course no two leaves are exactly alike, and perhaps no two drops of water are either; but that's  because 
these are very -complex bodies. The case is very different with the parts of -simple solid matter. And even  with 
complex bodies, it isn't impossible for God to make two of them-e.g. two drops of water-exactly alike. And if  he did 
make them exactly alike, their alikeness wouldn't turn them into a single drop of water! Their locations would be different,  even though 
it was absolutely indifferent which drop was placed in which location. The same reasoning holds regarding the choice between  this way and 
that way when God was giving the world of matter its initial shove. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="115" ref="71">5, 6 <ref n="16"/>  Two 
things don't stop being two by becoming exactly alike. The parts of -time are as exactly like each other as  are the 
parts of -space; yet two points of time aren't one and the same point of time
-'one thing with two names’. If God had created the world right now, it wouldn't have been  created at the time
			 when it actually was created. And if God did or could make the total bulk of matter 
finite in size, then the material universe would have to be in its nature movable; for  nothing that is finite is 
immovable. Thus, to say that God couldn't have made a different choice of when and where matter was 
to exist is -to make matter necessarily infinite and eternal, and -to reduce all things  to necessity and fate. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="116" ref="73">
7 <ref n="16"/> If the material world is finite in size, space outside the world is real, not  imaginary. And empty 
			spaces in the world aren't merely imaginary either. In a jar from which the air has been  pumped, a tiny quantity of 
			matter-rays of light, and perhaps other stuff-still remains, but the lack of  resistance plainly shows 
that most of that space is devoid of matter. The lack of resistance can 't be explained by the 
			matter's being very subtle, i.e. very finely divided: liquid mercury is as finely  divided and as fluid as water, yet 
it creates more than ten times as much resistance as water does; so its resistance  must arises from the quantity of 
			matter that is involved, not from the largeness of the matter' s parts; -which confirms my 
explanation of why the pumped-out jar offers so little resistance-.</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="117" ref="74"> 8 <ref n="16"/> Any region of empty space is 
the property of an incorporeal substance--a substance that isn't made of matter-. Space is not 
'bounded' by bodies, but exists equally within bodies and around them. Space isn't enclosed between 
bodies; rather, bodies exist in unbounded space and are terminated -or  boundaried or bounded- by their own dimensions. 
			<!-- Evidently meaning that what &apos;limits&apos; the size of a material thing is just  its size. -->
		</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="118" ref="75">9 <ref n="16"/> Empty 
			space is not 'an attribute without a subject’, because by  the phrase 'empty space’ 
we never mean 'space that is empty of everything’ but only 'space that is empty of 
body’. In all empty space
			God is certainly present, and possibly many other substances that aren't 
			matter-ones that can't be  felt by touch or detected by any of our other senses. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="119" ref="76">10 <ref n="17"/>
			Space
			 is not a substance, but a  property; and if it's a property of something that is necessary it will (like any 
other property of anything necessary) itself exist  necessarily; without being a substance, it will have a necessity of existence that 
contingent substances lack. -Space  is immense, unchangeable and eternal; and so also is -duration. But 
this doesn't at all imply that anything is  eternal other than God. For space and duration are not 
other than or additional to God
			<!-- Clarke twice uses the French hors de Dieu, echoing Leibniz&apos;s use of it inhis 
10 on page 8 --> ; they are caused by  his existence-are immediate and necessary consequences of his existence.7 And without them he 
wouldn't be eternal and omnipresent.</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="120" ref="77">11, 12 <ref n="17"/> -Infinites are composed of finites only in the sense in which -finites are 
composed of infinitesimals. I have already  explained, in my 3 on page 13, in what sense space has or doesn't have 
parts. In the body-related sense of the  word, 'parts' are separable, compounded, un-united, independent of each other, and movable from 
each other. In contrast with  that, although we can partly grasp or imaginatively conceive infinite space as composed 
of parts, those 'parts ' (improperly so-called) are essentially indiscernible from one another, immovable from one other, and not capable 
of being split  off, because the idea of splitting one off from the rest involves an explicit contradiction in terms (see my 4 on page 7, 
and my 3 on page  13). Thus, space is in itself essentially one, and absolutely indivisible. 'God is 
eternal and  infinite, omnipotent and omniscient. That is, he lasts from eternity to eternity, and is present from infinity to infinity. 
He governs  everything that exists, and knows everything that it is possible to know. He is not eternity or infinity, but 
is eternal  and infinite. He isn't duration or space, but he. . . endures through all time
			  and is present through all space; and by existing always and everywhere he establishes duration and 
			space. <!-- Newton writes constituit, which Clarke translates as &quot;constitutes&quot;, but Newton is 
using that  word in its now obsolete sense of &quot;establishes&quot; or &quot;sets up&quot;. --> Since every particle of space
			 is  always, and every indivisible moment of duration is everywhere, the maker and lord of all things cannot be never and 
nowhere. . . . His  omnipresence isn't just a matter of his power's being everywhere; a power can't exist without 
substance  -that has it-; so he himself is everywhere.' Newton, Principia, General scholium.</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="121" ref="79"> 13 <ref n="17"/> If the world is 
finite in size, it  can be moved by the power of God; so my argument based on that movableness is conclusive. Two 
exactly alike places are  not the same place. Nor are the universe's being in motion and its staying at rest the same state. If a ship is 
sailing smoothly  enough, a man shut up in the cabin can't tell whether it is moving or not; but that doesn't alter the 
fact that  its moving and its not moving are not the same state! Whether or not the locked-up man can detect it, the motion of the ship is 
a real  state with real effects (a different state and different effects from motionlessness); and if the ship suddenly stopped, that 
would yield  other real effects; as would a sudden stopping of an indiscernible motion of the universe. No answer to this argument has 
ever been given  -from Leibniz's side-. Newton emphasizes this at length in his Mathematical Principles, (Definition 8) 
where from  the consideration of the properties, causes, and effects of motion, he shows the difference between -real motion (a body's 
being  moved from one part of space to another) and -relative motion (bodies merely undergoing a change of the order 
or  situation they have with respect to one other). This argument is a mathematical one. It shows from real effects 
that  there may be real motion in the absence of relative motion, and relative motion in the absence of real motion. It isn't answered by  
simply asserting the contrary.</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="122" ref="80"> 14 <ref n="17"/> The reality of space is not a 'supposition’, but 
is proved by the above arguments, to which no answer has been given. Nor is any answer given to my other argument--in 4 on page  14—that 
			space and time are quantities, which situation and order are not. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="123" ref="81">15 <ref n="17"/> It wasn 't 
impossible for God to have made the world sooner or later than he actually did; and it's not at all  impossible for him 
to destroy it sooner or later than he actually will. As for the notion of the world's eternity: those who suppose matter
 and space to be the same must indeed suppose that not only is the world infinite and eternal but it 
necessarily must be so; just as necessarily as space and duration, which depend not on the will but on 
the existence of God. <!-- Leibniz, as he will say in his 62 on page 40, doesn&apos;t  &apos;suppose 
matter and space to be the same&apos;. This sentence of Clarke&apos;s seems to be a  side-swipe at 
Descartes: someone who combines -Descartes&apos;s view that matter is the same as space with 
-Clarke&apos;s own view about the nature of space and the necessity of  its existence will be 
forced to the conclusion that the material world exists necessarily. -->
			But  there is no problem here 
for those who believe that God created as much matter as he pleased, and  where and when he pleased. 
For God in his wisdom may have had very good reasons for creating this world at the  particular time 
that he chose; and he may have created other kinds of things before this material world began, and may  create yet further kinds of things 
after this world is destroyed.</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="124" ref="82"> 16, 17 <ref n="17"/> In my 4 on page 13 and my 13 on this page, I have  shown that space
			 and time are not the mere order of things, but are real quantities  (which order and 
situation are not). Leibniz hasn't answered those proofs. Until he does so, his assertion-which he says 'would  be a contradiction' if I 
were right-has to be regarded as indeed being a contradiction. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="125" ref="84">18 <ref n="18"/> The uniformity of all the  parts of space
			 isn't an argument against God's acting in any part in any way he likes. God may have good 
reasons to create finite beings, and finite beings have to be in particular places. All places are  basically alike (and would be so even 
if place were nothing but the situation of bodies); so when God  places two indistinguishable cubes of 
			matter this way rather than that, the two options are perfectly equal; but that doesn't mean that it is 
unworthy of the perfections of God that he should choose one of them. There  may be very good reasons why both the 
cubes should exist, and they can't exist except placed this way or that. -Also, Leibniz's  statement that 'A will without reason would be 
mere Epicurean chance' is wrong-. Epicurean chance is not a choice of will, but a blind necessity of fate. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="126" ref="85">19 <ref n
="18"/> This argument (as I observed in my 3-4 on page 22), if it proves anything,  proves that God didn't and can't 
create any matter at all. The options of different  initial locations for equal and exactly alike parts of 
matter would have to be indifferent; as was also the first-shove  determination of their motions-this way or the opposite way.
		</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="127" ref="86"> 20 <ref n="18"/> I don't see what this has to do with anything we have  been arguing about.</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="128" ref="87"> 21 <ref n="18"/> 'God
			 cannot set limits to how much matter there is' -that is too weighty an assertion to be accepted without 
proof. If he also can't limit how long matter lasts, then  the material world is both infinite and eternal necessarily 
and independently of God. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="129" ref="88">22, 23 <ref n="18"/> If this  argument were sound, it would prove that anything that 
			God can do is something that he must do-can't help doing;  so that he can't help making everything infinite and 
everything eternal. That would mean that he isn't a governor at all, but a mere necessary agent, i.e. not really an agent 
at all but mere fate and nature and  necessity.</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="130" ref="90"> 24-28 <ref n="8a"/> Concerning the use of the 
word sensorium <!-- this time Clarke uses the English  &apos;sensory&apos; --> , I have already said enough in my 10 on 
page 11, my 3 on page 7, and my 3 on page 1 (but bear in  mind that Newton says only '. . . as it were the sensorium. . . 
'). </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="131" ref="95">29 <ref n="18"/>
			Space is the place of  all things and of all ideas; just as duration is the duration of all 
things and of all ideas. This has no tendency to make God the soul of the world-see my 12 on page 8 
			<!-- Clarke might also have referred to his 12 on page 15. -->  There is no union between God and the world. It would 
be more proper to call the mind of man 'the soul of the images of things that it perceives' than to call God
			 'the soul of the  world'-the world to which he is present throughout, acting on it as he pleases without 
being acted on by it. I gave this answer in my  12 on page 14, but Leibniz repeats the same objection again and again, 
without taking any notice of my answer. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="132" ref="96">30 <ref n="25"/> I don't know what is meant by 'representative principle' <!-- see note in 
30 on page 19 --> . The soul discerns things by -having the images of them conveyed to it through the sense-organs; 
			God discerns things  by -being present to and in the substances of the things. Not by -producing them continually (for 
he is now resting from his work of  creation), but by -being continually omnipresent to everything that he created at the 
beginning. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="133" ref="97">31 <ref n="19"/> Leibniz  holds that -the soul doesn't act on the body; -the body moves purely in 
accord with -the laws of-  impact-mechanics; and yet -the body's movements conform to the will of the soul in all the 
infinite variety of  spontaneous animal motion. That is a perpetual miracle! 'Pre-established harmony' is just a phrase, an invented 
technical term.  It doesn't help in the slightest to explain this miraculous effect.</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="134" ref="98"> 32 <ref n="19"/> To suppose that in 
spontaneous animal motion the soul has no effect on matter, and that all spontaneous animal motion 
is performed through  impact-mechanics, is to reduce everything to mere fate and necessity. God acts on everything in 
the world, in any way  he likes, without any 'union' without being acted on by anything-all that shows plainly the difference between an 
omnipresent  governor and an imaginary soul of the world. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="135" ref="99">33 <ref n="19"/> In the nature of 
things, every action  is the giving of a new force to the thing that is acted on. Otherwise it's not really -action but  mere -passiveness; which is the case in all mechanical and inanimate passings-on of motion. <!-- The thought here is that 
when any  inanimate thing x makes something else y move, all x does is to pass on to y some motion which came to it from something else. 
In  inanimate systems motion is never originated. --> If the giving of a new force is supernatural, then every one of 
			God's actions is supernatural, and he has no role in the workings of the natural world. And it follows also that  
either -every human action is supernatural (-because it creates new force-) or -man is as much a mere machine as a  
clock is (-because he never creates new force-). </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="136" ref="100">34, 35 <ref n="19"/> I have already shown the difference 
between -the  true notion of God and -the notion of a soul of the world. See my 12 on page 11 and my 
29 and 32  just above. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="137" ref="102">36 <ref n="19"/> This has been answered in my 31 above.</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="138" ref="103"> 37 <ref n="19"/> The soul 
is not 'diffused  throughout the brain'. It is present in one particular place, the sensorium.</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="139" ref="104"> 38 <ref n="19"/> This is a bare 
assertion, without  proof. When two perfectly inelastic bodies meet in a head-on collision in which their forces are 
equal, they both lose  their motion. And Newton has given a mathematical example in which the amount of motion is 
continually falling and  rising, without any of it being passed on to other bodies (Optics, near end of Query 31).</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="140" ref="105"> 39 <ref n="19"/> 
This loss of force is not a 'defect', as Leibniz here supposes. It is the just and proper nature of 
inert matter. </Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="141" ref="106">40 <ref n="20"/> If this argument is sound, it proves that -the material world must be infinite, 
-that it must have  existed from eternity and must continue to eternity, and -that God must always have created as many 
men, and as many  things of every other kind, as it was possible for him to create, and to have gone on doing this for as long a 
time as  it was possible for him to do it. <!-- This item seems irrelevant to Leibniz&apos;s 40 on page 20; it is closer to 
fitting his 23 on page  18. See Leibniz&apos;s puzzled comment on itin his 103 on page 45. -->
		</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="142" ref="107"> 41 <ref n="20"/> I don't understand 
the words the order (or  situation) that makes it possible for bodies to be situated. It seems to amount to saying that situation is the 
cause of situation. <!--  Leibniz had written only of &apos;the order which &apos; etc.; the insertion of &apos;(or situation)&apos; was 
Clarke&apos;s. --> As I  point out in my 13 and 14 two pages back, it has been shown that space is not merely the order 
of bodies, and Leibniz  has not answered this. Also, it is obvious that time is not merely the order of things 
succeeding each other, because  the -quantity of time may be greater or less while the -order of events remains the 
same. . . . If there were no  created things, space and duration would be exactly the same as they are in actuality-
			God's  ubiquity <!-- = &apos;everywhereness&apos; --> and the continuance of his existence would see to that.</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="143" ref="108"> 42 
			<ref n="20"/> This is appealing  from reason to vulgar opinion, which philosophers should not do, because it is not the rule of truth. 
			<!-- Leibniz in his 107 on page 46  thinks Clarke is referring to the &apos;vulgar opinion&apos; that the ordinary concept of miracle 
shouldn&apos;t be used in science. He,  of course, couldn&apos;t know that Clarke in translating what he had written would omit the 
mention of how science should be done. -->
		</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="144" ref="109"> 43 <ref n="20"/> The concept of miracle does include unusualness. Think of things we 
count as 'natural' although they are  absolutely wonderful and manifest enormous amounts of power-things like the movements of the 
heavenly bodies, and the generation and  formation of plants and animals etc. Astounding as these are, they aren't miracles, simply 
because they are common, usual. But it doesn't follow that everything unusual is a miracle. It might instead be only an 
irregular and rarer effect of usual  causes-for example, eclipses, monstrous births <!-- see note to 43 on page 20 --> , madness in men, 
and countless other things that the  vulgar call prodigies.</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="145" ref="110"> 44 <ref n="20"/> This concedes what I claimed; though it's contrary to 
the common theological opinion to  suppose that an angel can perform a miracle.</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="146" ref="111"> 45 <ref n="20"/> That one body should attract 
another -from a distance- without any  intermediate means-indeed this isn't a -miracle because it's -a contradiction! That's because it 
supposes something to act  where it is not. But the means by which two bodies attract each other may be invisible and 
intangible, quite different  from mechanism, and yet be something that acts so regularly and constantly that we can call it 'natural'-it's 
much less  wonderful than animal motion, though that is never called a miracle. <!-- In these remarks of Clarke&apos;s and in 
Leibniz&apos;s response  to them in his 118 on page 48, moyen = &apos;means&apos; is apparently being used in two senses at once. -There 
is no how concerning the  attraction they are talking about, no means by which it is brought about; it just happens. But 
the absence of a moyen is  also -the absence of any intervening link between the mutually attracting bodies. -->
		</Utterance>
		<Utterance genid="147" ref="112">46 <ref n="20"/> 
If this is about forces that are 'natural' in the sense of being 'mechanical', then Leibniz is implying that all 
animals, all men  even, are mere machines-as much so as a clock. But if 'natural' doesn't mean 'mechanical', then  
gravitation may be brought about by forces that are regular and natural without being mechanical. <!-- Here and  
throughout, &apos;mechanical&apos; and its cognates refer to the physics of collisions-impact-mechanics. --> N.B. <ref n="21"/> The  
arguments offered in the postscript to Leibniz's fourth paper have been already answered in my replies above. All I need add here is  that 
his view about the impossibility of atoms (physical atoms, that is; we aren't arguing about mathematical  atoms) is an 
obvious absurdity. Either -there are perfectly solid particles of matter or -there are not. -If there are,  then 
there's nothing conceptually wrong with supposing that they have parts that are all of the same size and shape; and those parts  would be 
physical atoms that were perfectly alike. But -if there aren't any such perfectly solid particles, then there 's no 
			matter at all in the universe. Here is why: When you divide and subdivide the parts of a body, trying to get  down to 
the level where there are perfectly solid parts with no pores in them, the longer it takes you to reach that level the greater is  the 
proportion of pores to solid matter in that body. -That's because at each level you will have a mixture of  pores and 
			matter, and at each stage the matter you've reached is itself a mixture of pores and matter
			, which. . . etc.- So if your division-and-subdivision goes on to infinity without your ever arriving at parts  that are 
perfectly solid, i.e. contain no pores, it will follow that all bodies consist of pores only, without any matter at 
all; which is plainly absurd. And the same pattern of argument applies with regard to the matter of which  the bodies 
of any particular species are composed.</Utterance>
	</Turn>
	</Body>
</Dialog>